<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl" ?>

<article
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	version="5.0" xml:lang="en">

  <title>The Thatcher effect in typography</title>

  <para>
  Near my home, on my dog-walking route, there's a small business called <quote>FDM.</quote>
  Their initials are emblazoned in 2000pt capitals on the side of the property.
  I don't know what it stands for, or what they do.
  The reason I bring them up is a one screamingly disrespectful disregard for typography,
    in what is an otherwise entirely sober Roman-esque sign.
  </para>

  <para>
  I'm going to first show it to you upside down, in a fictional billboard advertisement sponsored by the lovely Jayma Mays:

		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject widthclass="full">
				<imagedata fileref="static/thatcher-effect/flipped.png" />
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
 					<para>Delicious.</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
  </para>

  <para>
  Lovely—both of them sexy and sophisticated;
    both with subtle, clean curves that demand attention precisely due to their understatedness;
    both enticing you, by just giving a little away, to look further.
  </para>

  <para>Right?</para>

  <para>
  Yes, until the potential customer stops sitting in the driver's seat upside-down,
    or reverts from their hand-walking on the pavement:

		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject widthclass="full">
				<imagedata fileref="static/thatcher-effect/right-side-up.png" />
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
 					<para>WTF?</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
  </para>

  <para>
  WTF?!  Or should I say, MTF?
  The <quote>M</quote> has suddenly broken in two and fallen in on itself.
  Why was it considered a good idea to use an upside-down <quote>W</quote>
    in place of the <quote>M</quote>
    into which the artist had poured countless hours of labour
    in order to be completely unobtrusive?
  Is it intended as 'attention-grabbing'?
  It works; but not all publicity is good publicity—I'm going to have to find myself a new dog-walking route.
  </para>

  <para>
  <emphasis>
    p.s. I'm sorry, Jayma.
    Every stroke of the GIMP brush was like a dagger in your baby-soft skin.
    But it was in the name of Typography!
  </emphasis>
  </para>
</article>
